Guide to the Jewish Funeral Practices Committee of Greater Washington records, 1975-1991 MS2054
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Jewish Funeral Practices Committee of Greater Washington records
1975-1991
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Jewish Funeral Practices Committee of Greater Washington
MS2054
3 Linear Feet
Collection consist primarily of correspondence amongst members of the Jewish Funeral Practices Committee of Greater Washington and organizations involved with the Committee between 1976 until 1982. The collection includes letters, notes, legal documents, photographs, by-laws, publications, reports, newspaper clippings, publications, memos, and minutes.
no content
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
Some of these records were donated by J. Ventura to Bob Hausman.
Historical or Biographical Note
The Jewish Funeral Practices Committee of Greater Washington grew out of the Tifereth Israel Funeral Practices Study Group in 1976. The Study Group originated after an October 1975 retreat involving a discussion titled "The Righteous Community." A follow up meeting of the Tifereth Israel Social Action Committee on November 9, 1975, chaired by Harris Weinstein laid the groundwork for a funeral practices group to be formed. The group had nine meetings between November 19, 1975 and March 16, 1976. By May of 1976, The Funeral Practices Study Group became a committee within the Tifereth Israel Congregation. The three main points as outlined for the first meeting of November 1975 were simple and became the standard goals of the committee from that time on.
I. Cemetery Problems II. Funeral Directors and Funeral Practices III. Education of the Congregation and the community
With these basic ideas, the group set out to help the Jewish Community understand and manage a funeral in the most traditional as well as stress-free and cost effective way.
The Tifereth Israel Funeral Practices Study Group met with Mr. Edward Knapp, President of the Memorial Society of Metropolitan Washington on January 26, 1976. The meeting took place at the home of Bob Hausman. Mr. Knapp explained how his organization helps its members by negotiating with funeral homes and cemeteries. It also creates contracts with funeral homes, establishing common prices for its members. The Tifereth Israel Funeral Practices Study Group also began participating with the local Rabbinical Assembly and working with the Presidents Assembly to organize a community-wide interest. These actions not only created a name within the community by the work the group was doing, but also by working so closely with established groups with influence over the community.
By mid-June 1976, there was talk of a community organization to be formed and for Harris Weinstein to become the chairman. The Committee was formed and began to incorporate other congregations and interested parties into their meetings. On October 18, 1976, the Washington Hebrew Congregation Minutes of Board of directors Meeting read, "the Committee... has now become an all-Metropolitan area committee operating at varying levels. The Committee is trying to protect the bereaved from being exploited during a weak moment and to help families obtain and acceptable funeral at the lowest possible cost. Creating an educational brochure which would describe what to do and answer various questions on the subject." With the support of various different groups within the Jewish Community and membership from other congregations, the Jewish Funeral Practices Committee continued its work in securing education, prices, and good conditions for the Jewish Community.
Since 1975, people within the Greater Washington Region have been dedicating their time and effort to establish an understanding of Jewish Funeral Practices and to make it easily accessible for anyone who might need these services. The Jewish Funeral practices Committee works diligently to make an already difficult task as manageable as possible while still adhering to laws and customs and creating as little financial strain as possible. The Committee has served its community well and continues to do so today.
Collection Scope and Content
The records in this collection consist primarily of correspondence amongst members and organizations involved with the Committee between 1976 until 1982. The collection includes letters, notes, legal documents, photographs, by-laws, publications, reports, newspaper clippings, publications, memos, and minutes. The Committee includes members from approximately 30 area synagogues, havurot, and B'nai B'rith lodges. Their mission is to coordinate activities for and educate members about practices for Jewish funerals. The collection covers a wide range of topics concerning the Jewish community and their funeral practices. It also includes many area funeral homes and the changing prices of funeral over the years. These materials date from 1975 to 1991 with the bulk of the materials ranging from 1976 to 1982.
Collection Organization
Organized into five series: Administrative files; Conferences, workshops, seminars; Cemetery files; Funeral home files; and Audio/Visual files.
Funeral rites and ceremonies, Jewish; Audiotapes; Washington (D.C.); Photographs; Jewish Funeral Practices Committee of Greater Washington; Tifereth Israel Funeral Practices Study Group
- Administrative files, 1975-1991; MS2054 Series 1; 1.5 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series consists of correspondence agendas, memoranda, minutes, resolutions, community mailing lists, educational pamphlets, articles, reports, addresses, newsletter, budgets/expenditures, and newspaper clippings. The material covers the dates 1975-91, with the bulk covering 1976-82. These records relay the evolution of the committee including documents both related to the founding and early years of the committee and includes its administrative records. The correspondence is from members such as Bob Hausman, Harris Weinstein, J. Ventura of the Temple Israel Congregation.
  - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous (notes and undated items), 1975 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous (notes and undated items), 1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1977 January-April (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1977 May-August (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1977 September-December (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous (notes and undated items), 1977 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous (notes and undated items), 1978 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Articles, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - "Basic Guidelines" Pamphlet, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Community Mailing List, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Educational Pamphlets, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - General Information, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Jewish Funeral Practices Committee of Greater Washington Historical Papers (J. Ventura Collection), undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Mailings and Questionnaires, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Notes and Letters, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Temple Israel Funeral Practices Committee Historical Papers (J. Ventura Collection), undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Conferences workshops, seminars, 1977-1979; MS2054 Series 2; 0.5 Linear feet
  This series documents the various meetings, conferences, workshops, seminars, and conventions pertaining to Jewish funeral practices. These files provide legal documentation for the better understanding of Jewish Funeral practices of the Greater Washington area such as DC Funeral Practices Act of 1979 and the Actions of City Council from June 16, 1978. The documents help establish the general guidelines that were set for funeral practices, focusing mainly on the late 1970's.
  - Conference on Jewish Funeral Practices, 1978 October 29 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Actions of City Council, 1978 June 16 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Workshop on Funeral Practices Seaboard Region, United Synagogue, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Workshop on Funeral Practices Seaboard Region, United Synagogue, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Seminar on Jewish Funeral Practices, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - United Synagogue Biennial Conventions, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - DC Funeral Practices Act, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Cemetery files, 1975-1991; MS2054 Series 3; 0.5 Linear feet
  This series documents the bulk of the committee's interactions with cemeteries in the area. including the Mt. Lebanon Cemetery, and the Jewish section of the cemetery within the Washington Memorial Park Cemetery. The files within this series contain legal papers, correspondence, notes, memos, tax papers, newsletters, and articles dating between 1975 and 1991.
  - Chevrah Tifereth Israel, Inc. VS Washington Memorial park, Inc., undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Chevrah Tifereth Israel, Inc. VS Washington Memorial Park, Inc., undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Mt. Lebanon Cemetery Associates VS Washington Memorial Park, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Litigation Research, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Mt. Lebanon Cemetery Associates, Inc., undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Mt. Lebanon Cemetery, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Mt. Lebanon Cemetery, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - George Washington Cemetery (Shaare Tefila and Mrs. Hoffman sites), undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Tax Related Paperwork, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Funeral home files, undated; MS2054 Series 4; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series document the committee's work with various funeral homes. The negotiations and planning for the committee to establish a contractual set price with funeral homes are included. The documents consist off correspondence, price lists, itemized lists of services, and memos.
  - Gilbert Jacoby, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Houser Rate Increases, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Minneapolis Plan, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Negotiations with Chambers Funeral Home, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Negotiations with Pearson's Funeral Home, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Audio/visual files, undated; MS2054 Series 5; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series contains photographs and audio materials. The photographs, originally in the Chevrah Tifereth Israel, Inc. VS Washington Memorial Park, Inc. file, show conditions at the cemetery. The audio materials are labeled with various congregation names on them.
  - Audio Materials, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)